Guide to the Helen E. Hokinson Cartoons for The New Yorker
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Portfolio 7, Series VII
  - 174. The Gramercy Park season begins. (Box 8, Folder 147)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 11 3/8 x 15". Title written in pencil at head of drawing, and cancelled. A5156 written in pencil with portions cut away.
  - 175. [Matron with Scottie on leash viewing tower of Pisa.], 1931 (Box 10, Folder 237)
    Watercolor over pencil, 8 x 11", unsigned. Rough sketch for cover published April 25, 1931.
  - 176. [Chair of ladies club and young performer.] (Box 8, Folder 148)
    Pencil, 16 3/4 x 13 7/8", rough sketch, unsigned. Small tears in right margin.
  - 177. "Herbert, our car has been acting up again." (Box 8, Folder 149)
    Crayon, 13 3/4 x 16 7/8", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing, and typed on a slip attached to the drawing.
  - 178. "What can we do to prove to everybody that we have a sense of humor?" (Box 8, Folder 150)
    Pencil, 14 x 16 7/8", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over previously erased partially visible caption.
  - 179. "Whatever happened to those inexpensive little islands off the coast of Spain?" (Box 8, Folder 151)
    Pencil, 12 1/4 x 18 5/8", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over previously erased partially visible caption.
  - 180. "I'm really very cross with your cousin Alberta for sending me those coasters with poodles on them!" (Box 8, Folder 152)
    Pencil, 13 3/4 x 17", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing below, over, and above previously erased and partially visible notation and captions, and typed on a slip attached to the drawing.
  - 181. "Mr. Kirby went too far this morning. He said turnip tops were good enough for anybody!" (Box 8, Folder 153)
    Pencil, 12 x 18 3/4", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over previously erased caption.
  - 182. "You know, this year I'm almost tempted to let Walter surprise me." (Box 15, Folder 344)
    Pencil, 12 1/4 x 18 1/2", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing.
  - 183. [Matron with two framed paintings.] (Box 8, Folder 154)
    Pencil, 13 3/4 x 16 3/4", unsigned.
  - 184. "Vassar has certainly changed since we were there. My daughter tells me the only man they're crazy about is Vice Pres. Wallace." (Box 8, Folder 155)
    Pencil, 13 3/4 x 16 3/4", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over previously erased caption. Notation—about to go up to the Vassar Club—in right margin. Tears in left and right margins.
  - 185. [Large matron and small spouse at clothing store muffler (scarf) counter.] (Box 10, Folder 238)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 5 1/2 x 6 3/8", unsigned. N.Y. written in pencil on verso. Drawing related to #31 in Portfolio #2 and to #113 and #186 in Portfolio 3.
  - 186. Buying a Muffler. (Box 10, Folder 239)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 6 1/4 x 6 5/8", unsigned. Title written in pencil at head of drawing. N.Y. written in pencil on verso. Drawing related to #31 in Portfolio #2 and to #113 and #185 in Portfolio #3.
  - 187. "If there was only some way of finding out what Swampscott's mood is going to be!" (Box 9, Folder 156)
    pencil, 14 x 18", unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over previously erased caption.
  - 188. "Next year the real estate man is going to try to squeeze me into Westport." (Box 9, Folder 157)
    Pencil, 14 3/8 x 17 3/8'', rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over previously erased caption.
  - 189. "Do you think we'll ever get thru having Foreign Affairs?" (Box 9, Folder 158)
    Or "Now tell us what the Dutch really are doing in Indonesia?" Pencil, 12 1/4 x 18 3/4", rough sketch, unsigned. Captions written in pencil at foot of drawing over previously erased partially visible captions. Erased but visible notation in lower left corner.
  - 190. "Have we forgiven Spain yet?" (Box 9, Folder 159)
    Pencil, 11 7/8 x 17 7/8", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over previously erased partially visible captions. Alternate caption—"Will all those who are interested in going through an aluminum plant please raise their hands?"—typed on a slip attached to drawing.
  - 191. [Matron selling fresh vegetables along side of road in front of her estate.] (Box 9, Folder 160)
    Black ink and watercolor over pencil, 13 1/4 x 10 1/4", unsigned. Notation—Mrs. Newcombe—written in pencil in right margin. Rough sketch for cover.
  - 192. Ye quaint registration booth. (Box 9, Folder 161)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 17 3/4 x 11 1/2", unsigned. Title written in pencil at foot of drawing, and cancelled. A4770 written in black crayon on verso.
  - 193. "There's no future in a place like Bryn Mawr.", 1930 (Box 15, Folder 345)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 19 x 14 3/4". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing. A7400 written in blue crayon and date Nov 29.30 in pencil on verso. Has paper window mat with hanging loop attached.
  - 194. [Matron with tree limb cutter contemplating cutting sunflower.] (Box 9, Folder 162)
    Pencil, with sunflower in watercolor, 16 3/4 x 13 3/4", unsigned. Rough sketch for cover.
  - 195. [Housemaid in window contemplating scenery out window.] (Box 9, Folder 163)
    Watercolor over pencil, 12 x 9 1/2", unsigned. Rough sketch for a cover.
  - 196. [Chauffeur helping matron learn to ride bicycle.] (Box 9, Folder 164)
    Watercolor over pencil, 16 7/8 x 13 3/4", unsigned. Notation—Many chauffeurs will be put into this kind of service—written in pencil in lower left corner. Rough sketch for cover.
  - 197. [Four matrons seated at a table having 4th of July party.] (Box 9, Folder 165)
    Colored crayons over pencil, 17 x 14", unsigned. Rough sketch for a cover.
  - 198. "Are Alfred and Mary Dunhill married?" (Box 15, Folder 346)
    Pencil, 12 x 18 5/8", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing and typed on a slip attached to the drawing. Notation—No—written in pencil on a slip attached to drawing.
  - 199. The girls having luncheon party in a summer tea shoppe looking for place cards. (Box 15, Folder 347)
    Black ink and watercolors over pencil and crayon, 17 7/8 x 14", unsigned. Title written in pencil in upper right margin. Rough sketch for a cover.
  - 200. "But our lease says the Saturday after Labor Day." (Box 9, Folder 166)
    Pencil, 14 x 16 7/8", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing.
  - 201. "Do you mind if we just peek in the window?" (Box 9, Folder 167)
    (Or, they could be talking to each other and saying: "Do you think they would mind if we just peeked in the window?" pencil, 16 3/4 x 13 3/4", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing, and typed on a slip attached to the drawing.
  - 202. Ladies club meeting. (Box 9, Folder 168)
    Black ink over pencil, 14 3/4 x 17 5/8", rough sketch, unsigned.
  - 203. "Oh Mr. Cotton, do you play bridge?" (Box 9, Folder 169)
    Pencil, 13 3/4 x 16 3/4", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing. Remains of a slip containing typed alternate caption attached to drawing. Notation—mail man—written in pencil in lower left corner.